Let's now look at the route function.
The easiest way to create a route is directly from the navigation window using the
route button. Clicking it takes you to the route
editor. The map view remains the same, but the button bar on the right has changed.
We'll now show you how to create a route, where to enter waypoints,
and so on. Step one: Click
in the route widget in the lower left corner and create a new route by
giving it a new name by clicking "New". We'll choose the name "Test" and confirm with "OK".
The dialog box will now display the new name. A second click on "OK" will add
the route "Test" to the widget, but of course, there are no waypoints yet.
Step two is setting waypoints. In AvNav, this is done by
placing the crosshairs on the point where you want to create a waypoint. Here, we'll choose the buoy west of
Drejö, or better yet, slightly to the side, for obvious reasons, and click the "After" button.
Now we'll create a second waypoint. It should guide us into the passage
between Drejö and Avernakö. So, the crosshair needs to go there,
then we press "After" again. If we forgot
that we want to place a third waypoint between waypoints one and two,
we can now place a third waypoint between the two by clicking "Before.
" This means waypoint number three will now be placed before the currently active waypoint two.
It will look like this. That worked well. Working with the crosshair might
seem a bit cumbersome at first compared to direct taps on the
touchscreen. However, in situations with a rapidly moving ship on a smaller
screen and cold fingers, you'll come to appreciate this method of operation.
Now it's time to learn about other routing functions, such as moving
an existing waypoint. For example, waypoint 1 should now
be moved to the approach to Aeroeskøbing. To do this, waypoint 1 must first
be selected. This is done by simply clicking directly on the waypoint in the map.
If that's too cumbersome or too cramped, you can also select the waypoint in the widget.
With waypoint 1 selected, the crosshair must be set to the new coordinates.
Clicking the "Shift" button will then move waypoint 1 there.
To delete a waypoint from the route, use the delete button. Of course,
you must first select the waypoint you want to delete – as shown above.
These are essentially the steps required to create a route.
You can now access further options by clicking the Tools button and then
"show waypoint buttons." Here, you can use the Next and Previous buttons
to navigate between waypoints if working in the widget or on the map is less convenient.
The Edit button allows you to edit each individual waypoint,
for example, to assign a new name. The Locate button lets you
quickly retrieve the selected waypoint and return it to the map window if the map
has been moved for any reason. You can also achieve this by
clicking the waypoint in the widget. There's always at least one other option, which is a good thing.
Now that all the entries are complete, we move on to step 3: activating the route.
This is done by clicking the Start button. Before doing so, you should double-check
which waypoint is currently active, as that's where the route will start. So, we'll set
waypoint 1 as the first starting point from our current position and click Start.
The route is now active, and the view returns to the normal navigation window.
The Start button changes to a Stop button. With this, you could deactivate the route
. You can also see that your route is now active because the widgets
display the route-related values: the distance to the next waypoint, the course to it, and,
in the RTE widget, the route length and ETA. Interesting functions can be accessed via the tools.
The route can be activated while the route is running. If you decide
to skip a waypoint without changing the route's direction,
the Skip button is the right choice: Select the waypoint to be skipped,
then click Skip, and the route will jump to the next waypoint. This can be helpful
if you've passed a waypoint so far away that reaching it
isn't acknowledged. Of course, the route can also be modified while running
by switching back to the route editor,
for example, to move a waypoint. Waypoint 2, for instance, should
be moved closer to the buoy. This is done, as explained previously, using the Shift key.
The change is applied immediately while the route is running. Saving the route
after it has been created or modified happens automatically in the background.
If you want to perform an XTE update after modifying the route
, click Restart. To see
where the route files are located, navigate to the Routes section in the menu.
All saved routes are listed there, and you can see that the "Test" route
was recently saved automatically. It can now be copied,
downloaded, or edited, and it can be placed as an overlay on a map.
These are things you can try out at your leisure.
What else is possible in the route section is pretty self-explanatory from the buttons.
One button deserves special mention: "connect.
" Normally, "connect" is active. This means that route operations are
executed on the server, and all connected displays show the same values.
If "connect" is deactivated, you can
try out and change different routes on a local display—the server continues to work with the original route. These routes are
only processed on the local display. When
working with a second display on a second device, the "connect" button should always be active
to ensure that the server and client (the second device) are connected. Otherwise,
saving a route remains limited to the local machine.
You can find more detailed information in the documentation. That concludes our guide to creating routes.